Guide to the Conference records: "Rethinking Women and Home Economics in the Twentieth Century."
Conference records: "Rethinking Women and Home Economics in the Twentieth Century."
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Conference records: "Rethinking Women and Home Economics in the Twentieth Century."
23-2-2720
New York State College of Human Ecology.
1.3 Cubic Feet.
Correspondence, audiocassettes, publicity, lists, and other administrative records of the conference at Cornell University.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Correspondence, audiocassettes, publicity, lists, and other administrative records of the conference at Cornell University.
SUBJECTS
Names:
New York State College of Human Ecology.
Subjects:
Home economics.; Women--Social conditions.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Panelists/Attendees
Box 1 Folders 1-61
Series II. Arrangements/Publicity
Box 1 Folders 62-76
Box 2 Folders 1-17
Series III. Cassette Tapes
Box 2
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Panelists/Attendees
  - Allen, Ruth - Commentary and Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Apple, Rina - University of Wisconsin - "Every Girl a Mother Home Economics and the Ideology of Motherhood, 1890-1950" (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Babbitt, Kathleen - SUNY Binghamton - "Alphabet Soup and Depression-Era Subsistence: NYS Extension and the New Deal Agencies of the 1930s" (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bates, Mercedes - Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Belesco, Warren - University of Maryland, Baltimore County - "Home Economists vs. Alternative Foodways" (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Brumberg, J.J. - Vita and correspondence (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bryant, Keith - Cornell University - Comments on Horowitz and Robinson Papers (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Cravens, Hamilton - Iowa State University - Correspondence and Vita (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Colman, Gould - Cornell University Archivist (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Conable, Charlotte W. - Resume and Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Cowan, Ruth Schwartz - SUNY, Stony Brook (facilitator/respondent) (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Davis, Audrey - Curator, The National Museum of American History (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Dean Firebaugh correspondence (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - DeVault, Eileen - ILR, Cornell University (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Dudden, Faye E. - Union College (facilitator/respondent) (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - East, Marjorie - panelist - correspondence and resume (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Furness, Betty (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Geistfeld, Loren - Ohio State University - Vita (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Gentzler, Yvonne S. - Resume and correspondence (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Goldsmith, Elizabeth - Invited Scholar - Florida State University (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Goldstein, Carolyn - University of Delaware - "Part of the Package?: Home Economists in Industry in the Interwar Period" (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Grant, Julia - Boston - "Modernizing Motherhood: Modernizing Motherhood and the Parent Education Movement, 1915-1940" (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Haber, Barbara - Schlesinger Library, Radcliffe College - "'You and Chocolate Cake': Betty Crocker's Message to Females in the 1950s" and recipes (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Harris, Carmen V. - Clemson University - "Grace Under Pressure: The Black Home Economics Agent in South Carolina, 1919-1967" (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Hopkins, Bernice (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Horowitz, Daniel - Smith College - "The Cultural Construction of Spending: American Household Budget Studies in the Early 20th Century" (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - James, Rae Jean - Bio, correspondence, resume (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Kline, Ronald - Cornell University - "Agents of Modernity: Home Economics and Rural Electrification in the United States, 1925-1950" (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Knowles, Jane B. - University of Wisconsin - "Domestic Science and Rural Women in the Midwest, 1900-1920 Two Examples from the Land Grant University Community" (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Khodtedt, Sally Gregory - University of Minnesota (facilitator/respondent) (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Lane, Ann J. - University of Virginia (facilitator/respondent) (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Levenstein, Harvey - McMaster University - "Home Economists and Ethnic Food" (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Low, Florence (commentator) - Bio, correspondence, newspaper article (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Mapes, Martha - correspondence and vita (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - McCray, Jacqueline - University of Arkansas at Pine Bluff - Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Meyer, Sibylle & Schulze, Eva - "Technology and Family: A Contribution to the Impact of Gender on Technological Development" (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Michel, Sonya - "A New Deal for Home Economics" (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Nerad, Maresi - University of California, Berkeley - "Gender and Status at the University of California at Berkeley: The Case of Home Economics 1918-1954" (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Newkirk, Gwendolyn - University of Nebraska, Lincoln (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Nyhart, Lynn - University of Wisconsin, Madison - "Home Economics in the American Hospital, 1900-1930" (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Past, Lois (Invited Scholar) (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Reed, Hazel - Bio, resume, correspondence (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Ricciuti, Henry - Commentator on Rima Apple's and Julia Grant's papers (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Robinson, Lisa - Michigan State University - "Safeguarded by your Refrigerator: Mary Engle Pennington and Industrial Home Economics" (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Ross, Alice - Hearth Studios - Vitae and brochure (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Rossiter, Margaret - "Men in Home Economics - A Contradiction in Terms?" (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Sicherman, Barbara - Trinity College (facilitator/respondent) (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Sklar, Kitty - SUNY Binghamton (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Smith, Ed - "Anna Bostford Comstock: Artist, Author, and Teacher" (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Stage, Sarah - UC Riverside - "'Home is not in the Kitchen' A New Look at Ellen Richards and the Home Economics Movement" (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - St. Marie, Satening - JC Penny Forum (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Thomas, Genevieve W. (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Tomes, Nancy Jane - Vita (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Vincent, Alison - "Theoretic Studies of 'Philanthropic' Interests of Women Educators" (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Vincenti, Virginia (panelist/facilitator) (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Washington, Margaret - "Home Economics, Industrial Education and the Penn School Challenge, 1863-1930" (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Weber, Rose Marie - SUNY Albany - Vita and correspondence (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Weigly, Emma S. (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - White, Suzanne - FDA - "'One Third Essence of Nothing': Home Economics as Consumer Advocates in the Cornell Bread Controversy, 1948-1950" (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Williams, E. Zabe - University of Wisconsin, Madison - "'Education for Living': The Definitions and Designs of the Lake Placid Conference on Home Economics, 1899-1908" (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Ziegler, Jerome M. - Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 61)
- Series II. Arrangements/Publicity
  - Mailing lists (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Home economists - possible conference participants (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Attendance records and final list of participants (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Panel of Home Economists, speakers, commentators (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Returned contracts (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Request forms and memos regarding room reservations, 1990-10-1991-05 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Budget/Receipts (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Caterers - correspondence, menus (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Exhibit at Olin (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Home Economics in film - An evening of historical films by and about the profession - from the National Archives and others (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Information on the Statler and local motels (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Official file (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Parking (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Funding - National Endowment for the Humanities and Cornell University (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Names and Addresses of People requesting copies of papers/tapes (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - New York Council for the Humanities - correspondence, funding, travel, Joan's final report (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Publicity - news releases, newspaper articles, mailings (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence regarding the Wolcott Letters, 1991-01-1991-03 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence regarding the 65th anniversary of the College of Human Ecology, 1989-01-1989-03 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence regarding possible material to be presented at conference, 1989-1990 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Dean's office correspondence, 1989-1991 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence with politicians (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - General correspondence to Brumberg and Bergstrom, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Responses to invitations to the conference, 1990-06-1990-07 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Responses from participants about the Conference, 1991-1992 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Applications for interpretive research (Endowment for the Humanities) and grants (National Science Foundation), 1989-1990 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Conference coordinator (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - External advisory group for conference (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Early home economics pamphlets (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - "Pioneers in Home Economics" by Flora Rose, Home Economics Bibliography, and "The Beginnings of Child Development and Family Life Education in the 20th Century" Lawrence Frank, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Folder of information for the conference (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Blueprints for agenda for conference printed at Typographics (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Prints and copies of old photographs (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Series III. Cassette Tapes
  - 1st session of conference (Box 2)
  - 1991-10-05 Alumni Auditorium 1:20pm (Box 2)
  - 1991-10-05 Alumni Aud. 3:00pm (Box 2)
  - 1991-10-05 Alumni Aud. 4:45pm (Box 2)
  - Intro by Eileen DeVault, Lynn Nyhart: "Home Economists in the Hospital, 1900-1930," Carolyn Goldstein: "Part of the Package: Home Economists in Industry During the Interwar Period," Lois Post: commentary - what is was like to be Betty Crocker (Box 2)
  - Intro by SG Khohlstedt, Sarah Stage on Ellen Swallow Richards and the Lake Placid conferences, Nancy Tomes "Spreading the Germ Theory" (Box 2)
  - Intro by Margaret Washington, Rose Marie Weber: "Starved for Something to Read: Literacy in the Cornell Reading Course for Farmers' Wives," Cramen Harris: "Grace Under Pressure: The African-American Home Economics Agent in South Carolina, 1919-1965," comment by Florence Low on papers and on black home economics agents in Texas in the 1930s, during WWII and during integration (Box 2)
  - Intro by Ann Lane, Rima Apple: "Every Girl a Mother: Home Economics and the Ideology of Motherhood, 1890-1950," Julia Grant: "Modernizing Mothers: Home Economics and the Parent Eduction Movement," Comments: Henry Ricciuti and Lane (Box 2)
  - Hersey (Box 2)